<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A prognostication for this yere M.D.xlvi, written by the experte docter of Astronomie [and] Phisicke Achilles. P. Gasser. L. Dominators are Mars [and] Luna</title>
            <author>Gasser, Achilles Pirmin, 1505-1577.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1546</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17732</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 447.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109861</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845504</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845504</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10409</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17732)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10409)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 67:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A prognostication for this yere M.D.xlvi, written by the experte docter of Astronomie [and] Phisicke Achilles. P. Gasser. L. Dominators are Mars [and] Luna</title>
                  <author>Gasser, Achilles Pirmin, 1505-1577.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[76] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Ex officina Richardi Graftoni clarissimo principi Edouardo typographia,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1546]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: a-d e⁶ (e6 is blank).</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 11646.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 11646 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Prognostication only.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: leaf a8 lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Almanacs, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10409:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10409:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> PROG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtication for this yere M. D. xlvi, written by the experte docter of Aſtronomie &amp; Phiſicke Archilles. P Gaſſer. L</p>
            <p>Dominators are Mars &amp; Luna.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10409:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10409:2"/>
            <head>Prognoſtication</head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>THE FIRST CHAPI<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter</hi> entreateth generally of the courſe of the planetes and vvhat vvether ſhalbe this yere.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS YERE (AS</hi> well for that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more parte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> planetes in eche figure of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at lodged in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery ſygnes or figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, as for that the Mone, ladi of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firmame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or whole worlde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd ſignes ſhal not ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue the comen &amp; accuſtomed power) ſhalbe moyſt with heate of the ayer and foule as concerning the ceaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>SPRYNG</hi> tyme namely, of which the moone ſhalbe lady with the ayde of Mars &amp; Iuppiter, ſhall be colde and moiſt with much wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and foule wether. <hi>SOMER</hi> vnto whom Mars and Mercury e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually
<pb facs="tcp:10409:3"/> ſhal gouerne, ſhal kepe tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate fayrenes, but yet often ſhall bruſt forth with ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dy thunderous wyndes. <hi>HERVEST</hi> ceaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whom Mercury with the helpe of Saturn &amp; Venus ſhal gouerne, ſhalbe wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, clowdy and ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>what rayny, but all together / variable and dyuerſe in heat. <hi>VVINTER</hi> which by Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus with thayd of Mars ſhalbe ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led, ſhall be very colde, with rayne and ſnow. Finally, theſe ar y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and ſuſpecte dayes of this whole yere .iiii.ix.xx. and .xxix. of Marche, the .vii.xv.xxii.xxiii. and xxix, of April. the .x.xvii. and xxx. of Maie, the .ii.xvii.xxiii, and xxviii. of Iuly, the fyrſte and .xix of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the .xx. and .xxvi. of October,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of the perticuler ceaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of euery Moneth in the yere.</head>
               <div n="January" type="month">
                  <head>Ianuary,</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> full Moone the ſeconde day the .iiii. houre xxiii. minute af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:10409:3"/> none, temperate as touchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g any gret colde, but on the morow ſnowy wyndes ſhall fall, &amp; euen ſo it ſhall come to paſſe on the .v, day, wherin the moone ſhall be ioyned vnto the clowdy ſterre that is in the head of Sagittary, &amp; Venus at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euening-tyde before the Sonne ſetteth with <hi>ARCTVR</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Wago<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> keper, a ſter ſo named, and is ſo called becauſe he foloweth the wagon that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Charlemaynes wayne of the vp landiſh, but of ſome, the Beare, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they moue about the Pole, as the Beare about the ſtake: &amp; of the learned, both he and the wagon are named <hi>BOETES</hi> becauſe they mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſlowly as Oxen do. The Poetes fayne that he was Iupiters ſonne, &amp; nominate <hi>ARCADES.</hi> but he is called <hi>ARCTVRVS</hi> for that he is girded rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d about w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern ſterres. The ſyxt daye whan Mars ryſeth or ſpringeth vp with the hert of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>SCORPION</hi> (an other name of a ſterre) before none, and the Sonne ſhalbe entred in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of Saturne, the ayer ſhall be
<pb facs="tcp:10409:4"/> troubled with rayne, paradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture vntyll the next day that the moone cloſe in the night with <hi>HYADES.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> fyrſt quarter ſhalbe the .ix. day vii houre before none, &amp; the cold ſhall not be much aſwaged. The ix. daye, whyleſt the Sonne ſhall ſpring with the Dolphi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or Porpoſe it ſhall ſnow. The .xiii. day, Mars riſyng with <hi>ARCTVR</hi> and <hi>SA<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>TVRNE</hi> ſette euen ouer againſte the Mone, ſhal cauſe a cloudy ſky, The xiiii. day, whan Venus ſetteth with <hi>FOMAHAND</hi> in the twy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>light, it ſhal ſnow. <hi>THE</hi> ful mone ſhalbe on the xvii. day at one of the clocke xvi mi, before none, whan Ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nus with the cloudy ſterre, that is in the head of <hi>SAGITTARI</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the Sonne, and Mercury after the ſonne ſhal ariſe with <hi>ALGOL</hi> moiſt windes ſhal blow, And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xix day whan Mercury in the morning after the Sonne ſhall ſpring with the Gottes tayle, and Mars in the night ſhall be in a quartyle aſpecte with the Mone, it ſhall ether ſnow or rayne, &amp; ſo ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinew the next
<pb facs="tcp:10409:4"/> day becauſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> openi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gate be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>twene Saturne &amp; the Mone, and on the xxi. day, becauſe the Sonne ſhal ſet with <hi>FOMAHAND,</hi> it ſhal peraduenture endure. On the xxiiii day, whan Iuppiter afore the Son in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euenyng, ſhalbe ouerwhelmed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Croune of <hi>ARIADNES</hi> and after that the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſelfe lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhal ſet with the Egle, the froſt ſomwhat ſhalbe relented or thawed</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> laſt quarter of the Mone ſhalbe the xxv. day at v. of the clock after none. On y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xxvii day whileſt Mars ſhall ryſe ere the Son ſhyne with <hi>ALKAYR,</hi> that is with the Egle or flyeng <hi>VVLTVRE</hi>) &amp; the Moone ſhalbe coupled with the ſame Mars at none, and afterward in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nyght ſhalbe coupled with Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne: &amp; further Venus in the twy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyght ſhall ſet with the Southerne Croune, cloudes &amp; wyndes ſhalbe rayſed. The xxxi. day, whyles the Sonne ſhall ſpring with the hed of <hi>MEDVSAE</hi> Mars ſhall aſcende with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hed of <hi>SERPENTARY</hi> in the day, &amp; in the nyght, the mone
<pb facs="tcp:10409:5"/> ſhalbe ioyned with the Gotes tayle the ayer ſhalbe troubled.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="February" type="month">
                  <head>February</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> new mone ſhalbe kyndled in a pyttie degree on the fyrſt day of February at ii. of the clocke .xlviii mi. afore noone, in which day alſo the Son ſhal ſettle with the Gotes tayle. Alſo on the ſecond day whan Mercury about none ſhalbe ioyned with the Moone, &amp; ſhal ſet at night after the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne with <hi>FIDICVLA</hi> the lytell ſtryng: Lykewyſe on the third dai, colde, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moiſt wi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des ſhal begyn to hurt. The v day, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus with the ſhulder of <hi>PEGASE</hi> ſhall ſpring in the mornyng, and in the nyght the two infortunate ſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſhal couple in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Eaſt parte of heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the aier ſhalbe troubleſom. The fyrſt quar, hapneth on the vii. day, the viii houre after none, with which lyght, the ſame Mone a lytel before Noone ſhall be ioyned with <hi>PLEIADES</hi> the .vii. Sterres, and Mars afore the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſhall ſet
<pb facs="tcp:10409:5"/> with <hi>ARCTVR,</hi> more hoate or warme rayne. The ix. day, clowdy. The xii. day whan Venus ſhalbe co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uered or ſet with <hi>FOMAHAND</hi> afore the Sonne, the Moone after the Sonne ſette, ſhall drawe nyghe the Racke and the lytel Aſſes: Alſo on the xiii. day, whyles the Sonne ſhalbe ioyned vnto the cloudy ſterre that is in the beginning of the ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng or powri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g out of the waterer or in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> figure Aquarius, &amp; at night ſhalbe ſet with thuttermoſt Ster of <hi>ERIDANI,</hi> ſnow &amp; ſtormes ſhal trouble the ayer. <hi>THE</hi> full Mone the v, day, the .vii. howre. the .lv. mi. after none, wi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dy w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moiſt &amp; vnſtable wether. On the xvii. day, rayne or ſnow ſhal fall, namely, whan Venꝰ in theueni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g before the goyng down of the Sonne, ſhall ioyne with the Egle &amp; the Gotes tayle. On the xix day, peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture the ſame tempeſt or wether ſhall endure, bicauſe that Iupiter with the hed of <hi>ANDRO<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>MEDE,</hi> in the day tyme, ſhalbe long before the Sonne, and Venus with the head of <hi>ALGOLE</hi> in
<pb facs="tcp:10409:6"/> lyke maner, a lytell before the Son aſcend or ryſe. <hi>THE</hi> laſt quarter ſhalbe the .xxiii, day at .viii. of the clocke afore Noone, in a pitty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, on which day, Mars, before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day ſpring, with a cloudy ſter, that is in the hed of Sagittary the Sho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, and alſo with the Snout of the lytell horſe, ſhall ryſe, &amp; the Moone not long after, with the ſame clow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſter in the ſhoters hed, ſhal holde a Synode or Counſell, that is, ſhe ſhalbe ioyned with the ſame ſterre, as men be ioyned in cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſels, which ſhall cauſe troublous wyndes, and ſhal contynue tyll the next day. On the xxv day y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cold ſhalbe rele<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, as well bicauſe that the Sonne ſhalbe ſet vnder or ioyned with the cloudy ſter, as alſo bycauſe that the Son in the ſame euening ſhall go doune or ſet with the tayle of the Whalle fiſh. On the xxviii day, it ſhal ether rayne or ſnow.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="March" type="month">
                  <head>Marche.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ON THE</hi> fyrſt day of Marche
<pb facs="tcp:10409:6"/> Venus, entering into the ſygne of Piſces, ſhall cauſe moyſtnes. <hi>THE</hi> new Moone <hi>EMBOLISMAL</hi> that is, the ſuperfluous Mone, ſhal appere on the ſecond day, &amp; xii. min. after the poyncte of the Mone, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, as touching colde &amp; here, but yet ſomwhat wyndy, &amp; enclyned to moyſtture. On the third day, whan Venus ſhall couple with the ſterre <hi>NEBVLOSE,</hi> &amp; that the ſterre called <hi>PORTE APERTIO,</hi> be betwene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sonne &amp; Saturne, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall it be colde wether, or ꝑchaunce hore or white froſtes, &amp; ſo it ſhal con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinue the next day, bicauſe the Son ſetteth with the Sterre, called the ſhoulder of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wynged or flie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g horſe On the vii. day, bicauſe Venus ſhal ioyne with <hi>FOMAHAND</hi> (which is the laſt ſter in the ſygne Aquariꝰ) afore myd day, &amp; the Son with the wombe or belly of <hi>PEGA<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>SE,</hi> at Noone ſhal ſpring or aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. and the Moone ſhall ioyne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>HY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ADES,</hi> &amp; at the laſt, the Son ſhal ſet w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the belly of the Whale fyſh: therfore the ayer ſhalbe ſomewhat
<pb facs="tcp:10409:7"/> moyſt. <hi>THE</hi> fyrſt quarter ſhalbe on the ix. daye, x. houre before myd day. variable or cloudy wether. On the x, days, for the euenes of the day and nyght in the ſpring tyme. And on the xi. day, for the ſettyng of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus with the harpe afore the Son, ther ſhal ſtyl out hote or ſowli rayn The xix day, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ayer ſhalbe troubled i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> like maner. <hi>THE</hi> ful, <hi>EMBOLIS MAL</hi> or od Mone, ſhalbe on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vii day one of the clocke xxxii mi. after None, not only in a puteall or pitty degree of both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyghtes, that is of both Sonne &amp; Moone: but alſo on the ſame day the Mone, or it be mid day ſhall ioyne with the Vyneyard keper: vnſtable tempeſtes ſhalbe pro longed euyn vnto the next day folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing, wherin Mars both ſetteth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>ARIADNES</hi> his Crowne, and the eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ing hath a iiii. coruerd aſpect vnto <hi>DIANA,</hi> that is the Mone, ſhall cauſe Northerne wyndes to blow. On the xx. day it ſhalbe rayn and perchaunce the next .iii. dayes folowyng, bycauſe the Sonne ſhall ſettle w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>MARKEB</hi> (that is with
<pb facs="tcp:10409:7"/> the ſhoulder of the great horſe) and w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the belly of the whale fiſh, except in ſome places, the Sterre, called <hi>PORTE ADPERTIO</hi> ſhall bring a hore or whyte froſte.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> laſt quar, ſhall happen in a vaporous or ſmoky degree on the xxv. day, vii. houre afore None, and Mars alſo ſhal ſpring in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hed of <hi>ANDROMEDE</hi> and therefore, trobleſome &amp; moiſt, or els ſnowy wether ſhall appere. On the xxx. day, rayne &amp; wynd ſhal blow.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> new Mone, ſhalbe renewed on the xxxi day of Marche .ix. houre xi. mi. after Noone, with clere and fayre wether, perchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with newe thunders.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="April" type="month">
                  <head>Aprill,</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ABOVT</hi> the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d day of Aprill the Sonne goyng downe wiih <hi>AL<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>PHERAT</hi> (that is with the ſter of the ſhyn of <hi>PEGASAE</hi> or gret horſe) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aier ſhalbe very trobleous. On the .v. daye, the ſter <hi>PORTE ADPERTIO,</hi> beyng betwene Saturne
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                        <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10409:8"/> the next daye folowing, may bring among our mountaynes more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſom wyndes. On the xxviii. day in the dawni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the day Venus is ioyned with <hi>ALGOLE,</hi> &amp; with in a lytell after Mercury with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CARNER</hi> before the Son ſhall aſcend vp into the myddes of heuen and at the laſt, Mercury being with <hi>RIGOLE,</hi> not long before the Sonne ſhall ſet, we may looke for a trobelous wether, &amp; perchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſnow On the xxix. daye, for as muche as Venus and <hi>PLIADES</hi> in the morning ſpring, ſhall go before the Sonne, and <hi>CILLENIVM</hi> ſhal be coupled with <hi>PHEBVS,</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye ſhall haue hote wyndes and hurtfull to the eares &amp; eyes, which ar to be feared &amp; dred. <hi>THE</hi> newe Mone, the laſt day ar .vi. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clocke xvi, mi. afore Noone, and lykewyſe the goyng together of the Moone with <hi>VIRGILIE</hi> that is the vii ſterres. &amp; the ioyni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of Mars with a Fyxt clowdy ſterre: &amp; finally the ioyning of the Soone with <hi>MAIA</hi> (one of the .vii, Syſters among the
<pb facs="tcp:10409:8"/> vii. ſterres, betoken windes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="May" type="month">
                  <head>Maye.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ABOVTE</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt day of May, Mercury ſhall ſpring ymedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after the Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, and ſhal ſhine vnder the ſonne beames with <hi>FO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAHAND,</hi> and Venꝰ alſo bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at nighte ſhalbe drouned vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>HORISON</hi> (out of our ſight) with <hi>RIGILE</hi> afore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sonne: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine on the nexte daye in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng the Sunne ſhalbe lifted vp w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>FOMAHAND</hi> &amp; the ſame ſhall attain &amp; poſſeſſe the middes of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with <hi>PLEIADES</hi> at none, &amp; Mercury alſo ſhalbe ioyned wyth the ſame heape or figure of ſterres. Furthermore, on the .iii. daye Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curi with <hi>PLEIADES</hi> &amp; the gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of <hi>ORION</hi> ſhal deſcend or go doune in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euenyng after the Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> line that endith our ſighte: and to theſe on the .iiii. daye the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid meſſenger of goddes (Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury) with the Dogge ſhall mete a litle after the ſunne ſet, which beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken lightnynges and hayl, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture
<pb facs="tcp:10409:9"/> ſnowe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mountai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, according to the expectation of our commune people. On y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .vi. daye Venꝰ ſhal riſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>FOMAHAND</hi> afore the ſunne, and with <hi>PLEIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DES</hi> a litle afore noone.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> firſt quarter of the Mone the .vii. day at .vii. of the clocke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter noone, and the couplyng of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus with <hi>VIRGILLIE</hi> the vii. ſterres, ſhall bryng in diuers fliyng fiers by night, The .ix. daye ſhalbe cloudy and thunderous, for the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſhal ſet at night bothe with the eye of Taurus (the bulle) and with the ſter <hi>SIRIA.</hi> On the, x. day it ſhall rayn very much, for both <hi>ADPER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIO PORTAE,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> opening of the gate, and the mone after none ſhalbe ioyned with <hi>PROTRIGERE,</hi> &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus at euen a litle afore the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing doune w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>PLEIADES</hi> &amp; with <hi>ORIONS</hi> girdle ſhal go vnder. On the .ii. daye Mercurius in folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng the ſunne ſhall aſſende wyth <hi>HYADES</hi> and Venus vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ames in going before the ſunne ſhall ſet w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>ALHABOR</hi> the great dogge
<pb facs="tcp:10409:9"/> Againe, on the .xii. daye Venus ſhal be ouerwhelmed with <hi>ALDEBA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAM</hi> (the bulles eye,) and Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius ſhall ryſe with the goate. On the .xiii. daye Mercurius ſhall ryſe with <hi>ALDEBARAM</hi> (the bulles eye) after the ſunne, and the ſunne ſhal ſpring vp w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>SVCCVLI</hi> the pigges. On the .xiiii. day alſo Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curius ſhal ſettle with the hedde of <hi>ALGOL</hi> after the ſunne goyng doune, therfore, for the ſpace of .iiii. daies thei ſhal geue &amp; bring in by ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes partly ſhowers partly thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> full Moone of Maye the xv. day, v. of the clocke .lvi. minutes after noone ſhalbe made windy and ſumwhat moyſty. The .xvii. &amp; .xviii daye ſhalbe mixed with reigne and thunder, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Marcury in the breke of the daye ſhall aſſende with the right ſhulder of <hi>ORION</hi> and at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> twilyght with the ſame ſterre both the ſunne and Venus ſhal ſette to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, but not without hayle. On the .xx. daye Phebus, the ſunne ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mornyng with <hi>HIADES,</hi> and after him Mercury with <hi>PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CYON,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10409:10"/> the litle dogge, which we call <hi>CANICVLA</hi> of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es that are called the <hi>CANICV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAR</hi> dayes take their name, at ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght goyng awaye ſhall cauſe moyſt wyndes to blowe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> laſt quarter of the Mone ſhalbe on the .xxii. day at .vii. of the clock after noone, it ſhal raine. The xxiii. daye Venus vnder the ſunne ſhal ſpring with the bulles eye, &amp; aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cende with the goate: and therefore the cloudes gathered together ſhall caſt oute thunder and lightnyng, ſo that the next daye, what for the ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng of the Sunne with the bulles eye and for the aſcending of Venus the tempeſt ſhall ſcarſely ceaſe. On the .xxvi. day, the ayre ſhalbe metly temperate, excepte the Sunne with <hi>RIGILE</hi> at noone, and after hym Mercury with the great dogge, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altyng, and Venus at night folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng the ſunne ſettyng with the hed of <hi>ALGOLE,</hi> and at the laſte Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnus goyng backewarde both on this day and on the next day deſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng with the Waggandriuer not
<pb facs="tcp:10409:10"/> muche after the ſunne ſet, ſhal ſode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſende furth rayne and hayle,. On the .xxvii. daye the ſunne ſettyng w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>GORGONS</hi> hed and Mars aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng in the night with <hi>FOMA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HAND,</hi> ſhal cauſe thunder.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> newe Mone ſhalbe in a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teall or pittie degree. On the .xxix. day of this preſent moneth of May at .iiii. of the clocke .x. minute, after noone, wherin at night Mercuri al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſhall ſette after the Sunne with bright <hi>HIDRIA</hi> or water pott, &amp; it ſhalbe temperate heate, ſumwhat cloudye and wyndye. Alſo the .xxx. and .xxxi. day becauſe Mercuri ſhal aſſende with the righte ſhoulder of <hi>ORION</hi> in the mornyng before the ſunne, therfore ye ſhall haue rayne,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="June" type="month">
                  <head>Iune.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ABOVTE</hi> the .ii. daye of Iune, whyleſt the Mone early in the mornyng ſhal go vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> racke vnder the yerth, and in the euening whileſt <hi>AD PERCIO PORTAE</hi> is betwene Saturne and the ſunne,
<pb facs="tcp:10409:11"/> hayle is to be looked for, but in the toppes of mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taines ſnowe. On the v. daye Mercury foloyng the ſunne ſhall ryſe with <hi>RIGYL,</hi> &amp; when Venus the folowyng mayde of the ſunne at nyghte ſhall goo vnder the yearth with <hi>ALGOMAISA,</hi> it ſhall thunder,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> fyrſt quarter of the Mone, ſhalbe the .vi. daye not muche afore noone, in ſo much, as Mars ſhal ſet with <hi>VVEGA,</hi> therfore a wyndy and moyſt tempeſt ſhall take place, whiche on the next daye Venus vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der entryng the ſygne Cancer the Crabbe, ſhall more increaſe. On the ix. daye, when Mars with the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne Croune early in the morning &amp; Venus ſprynging after the ſunne with the ſterre of the fyrſt hedde, of the twine, whiche twine is called Gemini the ſigne. Alſo, on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .x. daye the ſunne departing away with the lytle dogge ſhall cauſe ſmall wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and thunder. The ſtandyng or ſteiyng of the ſunne (that is whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is at the higheſt and can go no hier) in Sommer ſhalbe on the .xii. daye.
<pb facs="tcp:10409:11"/> The .xiii. daye ſhalbe cloudye with lightnyng.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> ful moone ſhalbe the .xiiii day, at .ii. of the clock .xxx. minutes afore noone, wherin the ſunne ſhall aſſend in the mornyng with the hed of the firſt twine, and the mone ſhal be ioyned with the cloudy ſterre in the toppe of the hedde of the ſhoter or of the ſigne Sagittarye aboute noone, the wether ſhall be vnſtable with variable tempeſtes. On the .xv daye Venus ſhall ſpryng vp after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſunne wyth the hedde of the latter twine. On the xvi. day the ſame Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus late after the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſhal ſet with the bright water potte. On the .xvii daye Venus agayne ſhall ſpring af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſunne with the righte ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>ORION,</hi> and the Mone ſhal go together wyth the goates tayle, whiche ſhal cauſe muche lightnyng and ſumwhere haile: which tempeſt euen on the next daye, the ſunne ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng with <hi>ORIONS</hi> left ſhulder, and amounting with the great dog, ioyned vnto him onely in length, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward the <hi>Mone</hi> appliyng vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10409:12"/> cloudye ſterre of the water powred out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waterer, at after noone ſhal augment with moiſt thunder.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> laſte quarter ſhalbe the xx. day the .xi. of the clocke after no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne wyndye. On the .xxii. daye, the ſunne with the hedde of the hynder twine, and furthwyth after Venus with <hi>RIGILLE</hi> aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng ſhal mixe thunder with heate, except the couplyng of Venus and Mercury on the morowe ſende furthe rayne. On the .xxiiii. daye in the morning, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſunne ſpringyng with <hi>ORIONS</hi> right ſhulder, and at euen the Mone coupled with <hi>HIADES,</hi> Likwiſe on the .xxv. daye, the ſunne ſettyng wyth <hi>ALPHARD,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bright wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pott, ſhal powre out many thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry ſhowers. On y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xxvii. day Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury goyng backward ryſing in the mornyng with <hi>RIGILE,</hi> ſhal ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede the ſunne, and afterward again ſhall clyme into the hearte of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with <hi>ALGOMEISA.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> newe Moone ſhalbe on the xxviii. day at .iii. of the clocke .xxiiii minutes afore noone, and ſhal bring
<pb facs="tcp:10409:12"/> furth whote wyndes, but not verye muche healthſum, nor yet withoute moyſtnes. On the .xxx. day, the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne going vnder the eaſt with <hi>RIGIL</hi> and after in the myddes of heauen, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>ALGOMAISA</hi> ſhall cauſe heate a litle to abate.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="July" type="month">
                  <head>Iuly.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ON</hi> the firſt day of Iuly, Venus ioyned with the racke, ſhall ſet with it after the ſunne, and it ſhall thunder. On the .iii. daye Mars ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng betwene day and nyght wyth <hi>MARKEB,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhulder of the great horſe and Iupiter in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſigne Aquari or waterer ſet ouer agaynſt Venus in a ſtreighte lyne deuidyng the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle in the middes, ſhal bring in raine vntyll the next day, wherin Venus ſhal ryſe vp after the ſunne with the lytle hogge and the Moone ſhall go beyond the Grape gatherer at after noone.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> firſt quarter of the Mone ſhalbe on the .vi. daye afore none, at iiii. of the clock: in whiche the <hi>CA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NICVLER</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10409:13"/> or dog dayes begyn and the heate ſhalbe doubled wyth lightning On the .x. day the darke heauen ſhal yelde mortall diſeaſes. On the .xii. day Venus aſſending in the day with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> litle dogge ſhal raiſe vp whote wind and thunder.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> ful Mone the .xiii. day at .i. of the clocke .xxvi. minu. after none. On the .xiiii. day whyleſt the ſunne entryng the Lyon, ſhall ſpring with the rack &amp; the Mone at night ſhalbe copled with the Goates taile. On y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xv. and .xvi. daye, when Phebus the Sunne ſhal ryſe with the litle dogge ſterre in the mornyng, &amp; at euen ſhal go donne with the racke and hedde of the firſt twine, <hi>PRODROMI</hi> the aforerunners ſhall bryng thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and lightning, and parauenture a great hayl ſhal fal. The .xviii. day when fayre Venus with the prynce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſterre of the Lyon ſhall ſet after the Sunne, heate ſhalbe doubled.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> laſt quarter of the Moone the .xx. daye, at .iiii. of the clocke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore noone, in whych day alſo Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curye afore the Sunne ſhall aſſende
<pb facs="tcp:10409:13"/> with <hi>RIGOLE</hi> and ſhal amount with the greate Beare, and at laſte the ſame Venus ſhall goo vnder the hearte of heauen with <hi>RIGOLE</hi> therefore a varyable tempeſt ſhall ryſe, and perauenture it ſhall rayne aboundauntly, vnto whyche on the next day Venus ryſyng in the breke of daye wyth <hi>RIGOLE</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Moone commyng wyth the vii. ſterres, ſhalbe contrary. On the xxii. daye, the heate ſhall ſumwhat abate. On the .xxv. daye the Sunne aſſendyng in the mornyng wyth the Dogge, from whiche day, the dogge dayes haue theyr name. Alſo on the xxvi. daye Venus in the morning entryng the Virgin (or ſygne of the Virgyn) and the Moone at nyghte commyng to the racke, ſhall brynge furth moyſt windes and thunder.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> new Moone ſhalbe in a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teal or pitty degree on the .xxvii. dai of this preſent moneth, at .iiii. of the clocke .xl. minutes, after noone, and it ſhalbe whote, &amp; inclyned to thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and eaſt or ſoutheaſt wynde. On the xxviii. day Venus ſhal aſſend in
<pb facs="tcp:10409:14"/> the mornyng afore the ſunne wyth the bright water potte, and that the Sonne ſelfe ſhal clyme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame bright water potte at myd day, and therto Mercurius ſhall go doune afore the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſet with <hi>HERCVLES</hi> hed On the .xxix. day aboute noone, the openyng of the gate ſhalbe betwixt the backward going of Iupiter and Mercury, and at nyghte Mercurye ſhall ſet with the litle aſſes, and the racke. On the .xxx. day Mercury in the morning afore the ſunne wyth the racke, and afterward the ſunne ſelfe ſhall ryſe with the vttermoſte ſterre of <hi>ERIDANVS,</hi> &amp; afterward Mercury ſhall clyme into the heart of heauen afore noone agayne with the litle aſſes, at laſt the ſame Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury ſhal ſet afore the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne at night w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>APPOLLIVS</hi> head, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore worſe tempeſtes ſhalbe in great valleis, but on the mounteines in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery place ſharper ſhall aryſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="August" type="month">
                  <head>Auguſt.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10409:14"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ABOVTE</hi> the .iii. day of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt, whyleſt Venus ſhall riſe after the ſunne with the lions taile, a cloudy ſkye ſhall appeare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> fyrſt quarter of the Mone ſhalbe the .iiii. daye, at eyght of the clocke, after none, in a miſty or ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kie degree, and ſhalbe whote &amp; win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. On the .vi. daye in the mornyng Mercury ſpryngyng with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greate dogge, and the ſunne walking with the princelye ſterre of the lyon ſhall make or cauſe a thundry and windy tempeſt with cloudes. On y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .ix. day it ſhall reigne, and likewyſe on the x. day: wherin Venus in the breake of the daye clymeth with the lyons tayle, &amp; ſetteth afore the ſunne with the hearte of the ſame ymage of the lyon.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> ful Moone ſhalbe the .xi. day at .ix. of the clocke .xxxv. minu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, after noone and the eyre ſhall waxe colde and moyſte. On the .xii. daye, Mercury, not only in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng ſhall ſpryng afore the Sunne wyth <hi>RIGVLLE,</hi> but alſo with the ſame <hi>REGVLLE</hi> ſhal paſſe
<pb facs="tcp:10409:15"/> vnder themiddes of heauen, and the Mone ioyned with the cloudye ſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, ſhal get and procure wynd. On the .xiiii. daye it ſhall thunder and lyghten, and the Dogge tyme ſhall finyſſhe or ende. On the .xvi. daye in the mornyng whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Sunne aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng the line ending the ſight, with the brighte ſterre of the water potte ſhal bryng temperatenes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> laſt quarter ſhall be the .xviii. daye aboute noone, and ſhall reyſe vp vnſtable wyndes. On the .xxi. daye Venus ſhall ſpryng vp af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Sunne, wyth the Waggan driuer. On the .xxii. day Venus ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto <hi>PROTRIGETER,</hi> and contrary or euen agayne Mars ſhall make an openyng of the gate, and ſhall bryng furth rayne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> new Mone ſhalbe the .xxvi daye. the .viii. houre and .iiii. minu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes afore noone, in whych daye Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus after the Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſhal ſpring with the Northren crowne, wherfore the eyre ſhall geue awyndye moyſture with muche thunder. On the .xxvii. day late in the euenyng Venus ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:10409:15"/> ſette with the virgins eare of corne On the .xxviii. daye afore noone, the Mone ſhalbe ioyned in the length of the <hi>ZODIAC</hi> with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>EVIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DEMIATOR</hi> or the Grapega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer. The heat of Summer ſhal be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynne to be wythdrawne by rayne, and that forbecauſe Venus ſettyng both with the taile and backe of the Lyon after the Sunne, ſhe ſhall not ryſe and auaunce agayne in the end of Auguſt withoute ſnowe among the mountaynes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="September" type="month">
                  <head>September.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE ADPERTIO POR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAE</hi> or openyng of the gate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene Saturne and the Sunne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng on the firſt daye of September not farre from noone, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſhall folowe not muche after wyth <hi>AZIMECH</hi> or the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyns eare of corne, the ayre ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynne too be chaunged into harueſt ſhowers.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10409:16"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> firſt quarter of the Mone ſhalbe the .iii. daye at .x. of the clock afore none. On which day alſo Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury with the Waggandriuer, and Venus ſhall ſpryng after the ſunne with the virgins eare of corne: noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and cloudy windes ſhal blowe On the .vi. day Mercury aſſendyng the lyne that endeth the ſight wyth <hi>ARIADNES</hi> croune, &amp; the .vii. daye the Moone aboute noone ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the goates taile ſhal geue rayne. On the .ix. daye in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>PROTRIGETER,</hi> and further, almoſt .ii. houres after Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus with the harpe: alſo at the laſte that ſlowe ſiccle bearer Saturne with the ſwifte Egle, not withoute ſtormes ſhall ſpryng.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> full Mone the .x, day at v. of the clocke .xlix. mi. before None, in the beginni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g hore froſtes, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly folowyng ſhall be wynde with vnſtable moyſtneſſe: for both Venus on the ſame daye ſhall paſſe with the cloudye ſterre, &amp; Mercury long after the Sonne. ſettyng with the Virgens eare of cornie ſhal giue
<pb facs="tcp:10409:16"/> them ſelfes to beholde Cupido. On the, xii. &amp; .xiii, likewyſe, for as moch as the Herueſt eueneſſe of daye and night ſhalbe, &amp; Mercury <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hal ſpring after the Sonne with the Virgyns eare of corne, and Venus ſhal go vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the myddes of heauen with the Wago<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> driuer. Alſo on the, xiiii. day whyleſt the Mone before none ſhall draw nygh vnto the .vii. ſterres, the ayer ſhalbe troubeled. <hi>THE</hi> laſt quarter ſhalbe about midnyght on the .xvi. day, on which day, the Son riſyng in the morning with the tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peſtious ſterre of the Wagon driuer if not rayne, yet peraduenture it ſhall gyue a whyte hoared froſt or ſnow. On the .xviii. day, Mercuriꝰ riſyng after the Sonne <hi>VVEGA</hi> the flieng <hi>VVLTER.</hi> And on the ix. daye the Mone early in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng coupled wyth the Racke: and farthermore Venus ſpryngyng af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Sunne with the bryght ſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of the balaunce and auaunſing, ioyned bodely with the more So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren balance, ſhal cauſe moiſt win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and cloudy. On the .xxiii. daye,
<pb facs="tcp:10409:17"/> in the mornyng, the Sonne ſhal ryſe with the Northerne croune, &amp; after Noone Marcury ſhall clymbe the myddes of heuen with the Wag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n driuer: Lykewyſe on the xxiiii. day the Moone afore Noone ſhall come to the Grape gatherer, and at night the Sonne ſhall ſette with the Vyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins care of corne, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence moiſt cloudes ſhall take place. <hi>THE</hi> new moone the .xxv. day at .i. of the clocke .x. mi. before None, ſhalbe va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riable and vnſtable with thunder in ſome places. On the .xxviii. daye in the morning the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne with the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen &amp; after him Marcury ſhall ryſe with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bright ſterres of the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, Agayne, on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xxix. day Venus ſhal mount with <hi>ARIADNES</hi> croune, and the Sonne ſhall ſette with the backe and tayle of the Lyon, and ar the laſt on the .xxx. daye, the Sonne aſcending the hert of heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the Virgyns eare of corne, ſhall cauſe a cloudy ſky.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="October" type="month">
                  <head>October.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10409:17"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> fyrſt day of October, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus with the hert of the Scorpion ſhall ſcaſely go doune in the eueni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g after the Sonne without trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome wyndes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> fyrſt quarter of the Mone ſhalbe the .xxii. day at .xi. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clock at after Noone, on whiche daye the Sonne in the mornyng ſhall ſpring with the Virgins eare of corne, and ſome cold rayne ſhal ſoone folow. The .v. day ſhalbe cloudy, The .vii. day a whyte froſt ſhall prepayre the gatheryng in of the Grapes.</p>
                  <p>The full Moone the nynth daye at ii, of the clocke. the liii. minute after noone, and Venus ſhall aſcend the myddes of heuen with <hi>ANTER</hi> therefore looke for colde Wyndes and ſomwhat moiſty on the morow and next day after: as well becauſe in the one, the Sonne in the morni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſhall ſpring with the lytel Stryng, as in the other in the very moment or poynte as it were of Noone, the Moone ſhal be put vnder the ſeuen Sterres.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10409:18"/>
                  <p>On the xiii. daye, as Venus in the breake of the daye ſhall ſwym with the Arow &amp; the Scorpions hert, and Saturne ſhalbe ſet contrary too the Moone by a ſtrayte lyne a lytell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore noone: euen ſo on the .xiiii. day the Son aſcending vp with the Wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>go<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> driuer ſhal cauſe cloudi or ſnowi wether. <hi>THE</hi> laſt quarter ſhalbe the, xvi. day at .iii of the clocke after none, on which day the Moone, not far from the Weſt corner, about the ſame tyme of Noone goynge to the Racke ſhall cauſe moyſt wyndes. On the .xx. daye, Mercury goyng backward ſhal ſpring with the moſt clere &amp; bright ſterres of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Balaunce and ioyned vnto the Sonne ſhal ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue a white hored froſt, which on the xxi. day folowing becauſe that the Son in the morning with the a fore ſayd bright ſterres of the Balaunce and after him Venus ſhall ſpringe with the Egle: and agayn at after Noone the Moone ſhalbe ioyned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>PROTRYGETER:</hi> and laſt of all the Sonne ſhall ſettle with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more ſouth Bowle of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Balaunce,
<pb facs="tcp:10409:18"/> wherfore the colde ſhal ſcace ceaſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> new Mone ſhalbe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xxiiii day at .vii. of the clocke &amp; the vii mi. after Noone, windy and moyſt, and peraduenture it ſhalbe more truly ſayd to be ſnow. On the, xxvii, day Saturnus ſhall begynne late to ſet with the Wagon driuer. On the xxviii, day, the Moone opening the gate vnto Saturne fyrſt in a windy ſygne, afterward ioyned to Venus in a pytte degree before Noone: a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gayn the ſame Venus goyng doune in the nyght with the Wagon dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhal ouer turne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue thicke cloudes or ſnow, On the .xxxi. day the cloudes ſhalbe caryed with gret wyndes, namely, becauſe the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſhal ſpring with the head of <hi>OPHI<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>VCHVS</hi> the Serpent holder, &amp; is hercules, for whyleſt he held a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent with his hand, he was by Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter tanſlated among the ſterres.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="November" type="month">
                  <head>Nouember.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> fyrſt quarter of the Mone ſhalbe the firſt day at .x. of the clok
<pb facs="tcp:10409:19"/> afore none &amp; ſhal continew vntyll y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> next day whyleſt the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne auau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeth with the bright northern croune, &amp; a litle after the Mone ſhalbe ioyned with the cloudy ſterre that is in the beginni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Water ſheder of the Waterer, &amp; therfore it ſhalbe colde &amp; wyndy. The .iiii. day, the ayer ſhal be vnquyet &amp; troublous. On the .v day whyleſt Venus ſhall ryſe in the breake of the daye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the cloudy ſter that is in the Shoters hed &amp; auau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with the fallyng Vulture or Gripe, &amp; the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ioyned with the lytell cloudy ſterre in the Scorpion, only ſetteth at nyght w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the herte of the ſame conſtellatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt the clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſhal bring furth &amp; deliuer ſnow.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> ful Moone ſhalbe the .viii day at one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clock .xvii. mi. before noone in a pytty degree, &amp; for that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Mone ſhal take her counſell w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the vii. ſterres &amp; after folowing w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>HIA<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>DES,</hi> it ſhal rayne: Theſe <hi>HIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DES</hi> ar .v. Sterres ſituate in the Bulles head, &amp; ar ſo called among the Bretians, of Hio, to rayn, for as oft as they either ſpring or ſet, it rai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth:
<pb facs="tcp:10409:19"/> but of the Latiniſtes they at named <hi>SVCCVLI,</hi> Pygges, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Swyne delyte to wallowe in myer that cometh of rayne,</p>
                  <p>On the .x. day Mercurius ſpringing before the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne with the bryghteſt ſterres of the Balaunce, and the Moone beholding Saturne ſet in a contrary ſpoke or lyne, ſygnifyeth a whyte hored froſt or ſnow. <hi>THE</hi> laſt quar. ſhalbe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, xv, daye, x. of the clocke afore noone, moyſt &amp; wyndy, The, xvii. it ſhall ſnow. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, xviii. day the ſonne ſhal ſpring w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>ANTARE</hi> &amp; Venus ſhal auaunce w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the flyeng Gripe. the, ix, dai Venus ſetteth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tallyng Gripe after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne. the, xx, the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne in the morning aſcendeth with the Harrow, &amp; Iupiter ſhal co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Swan or ſygnettes tayle betwene day &amp; nyght, The .xxi. day Mercury at night goeth away with <hi>ANTER</hi> afore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, wherfore al theſe .iiii, dayes either ſhalbe dar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kened with cloudes, or els vnquyet wyndes ſhall haue preheminence.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> new Moone the, xxiii. day ſcace halfe an houre before Noone ſhall ſende furth colde wynde, and
<pb facs="tcp:10409:20"/> in many places moyſt for the ſpace almoſt of two dayes. On the .xxvii, day cloudes, &amp; peraduenture ſnow ſhall ſtep <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, The .xxix, day the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne aſcendeth in the mornyng with the Egle, &amp; Mercury ſhall clymbe the middes of heuen with <hi>ARCTVR</hi> before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, not without whyrle wyndes. <hi>THE</hi> fyrſt quarter ſhal be the .xxx. day at .vii. of the clocke after Noone with cold and wynde,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="December" type="month">
                  <head>December,</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ABOVT</hi> the firſt day why leſt Mercury ſhal aſcend w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>ARCTVR</hi> early before the Sonne riſyng, &amp; as the Sonne ſelf ſhalbe couered with the Serpent holders head, the ayer ſhalbe troubleſom, which ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynue vntyll the next day. The .iiii. day it ſhall ſnow. The .v day why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt the Sonne ſhall ryſe with the halfe of the Dolphin in the morni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and at nyght ſhall go away to reſt with the Wagon driuer. On the vi. day whan Venus ſhall go doune in
<pb facs="tcp:10409:20"/> the nyght after the Sonne ſet with the vttermoſt ſter of the Shede wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, than looke for moyſt wyndes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> full Moone the .vii, daye at one of the clocke .xliii. min. after none: on which day becauſe Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury alſo ſhal ſpring with the Egle in the morning, ſnowy wyndes ſhal ryſe: and ſhall waxe bygger on the nexte day becauſe of Saturne ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with the Sonne. On the tenth day, the Mone ſhalbe ioyned to the Racke in the morning, and Venus after that ſhall come to the ſpring with the head of <hi>MEDVSA.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>On the .xi. day, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Venus ſhall ſette with the Egle and the Gotes tayle in the nyght, On the .xii. day whyleſt <hi>VVYNTER</hi> ſhal ſpring &amp; the Semewes dayes, Mars ſhall aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the lyne that endeth our ſight about None, with the .vii. Sterres and Mercury at nyght ſhal deſcend the ſame tyme with the Wagondri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and ſhall cauſe ſnowy rayne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> laſt quarter ſhalbe the .xv day at .vii. of the clocke before none vnſtedfaſt wether: for on the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:10409:21"/> daye the Sonne ſhall ryſe with the cloudy ſterre of the Shoters head, &amp; after with the fallyng Gripe ſhall aſcende <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hert of Heuen, The, xix. day, the Sonne and Mercury ſhall couple before Noone in a pitty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and Iupiter ſhall begyn to ſet late with the vttermoſt ſterre of the Shede water, for theſe cauſes ſnow ſhalbe loked for. <hi>THE</hi> new moone the .xxiii, day at, iiii, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clock .xvii, mi. before noone ſhall cauſe a thaw partely with wynde &amp; partely with moyſture. The .xxiiii. daye ſhall be cloudy and alſo ſnowy. The, xxviii day Venus applyeng vnto the clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſterre of the Shed water agayne ſhall geue ſnow or cloudes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE</hi> fyrſt quarter of the Mone ſhalbe the .xxx, day at .ii. of the clok after noone, on which day the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſhall auaunce in the myddes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Egle &amp; the ſtrow, &amp; at euen ſhall ſet with the northern crowne, therfore they betoken ſnow and rayn vntyll the nexte daye wherein Venus is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunſed with the Shed water.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:10409:21"/>
               <head>¶ Of generall ſignifications of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes. Of the Lorde of the yeare, and of certayne Coniunctions.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ALTHOVGH</hi> this yere of M.D.xlvi. be not blemyſſhed with any Eclippes neither of Sonne nor Moone, yet Mars ſygnifyer of the comen and vulgare people &amp; lord of the yere, &amp; here vnto alſo the aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the reuolution of the world, ſhall cauſe in all this yere the peple to be vnſtable and inconſtant. Alſo though they bring heuynes &amp; feares euery where, yet moſt of all in the Eſt parte, not without the gret hyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or vndoyng of many, &amp; alſo the loſſe &amp; deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of many catel. Furthermore, the ſame Mars in the ſayd reuolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſet ouer agaynſt the Moone: betokeneth corruption of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ayer, fyer flye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g by night, a blaſyng Sterre, ſundrye diſeaſes, &amp; finally the conſumyng by fyer of Vyllages and Cities, with infinite diſceytful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes. wherfore, let al thoſe peple that ar ſubiect to Capricorn thinke theſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto them. But the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Mars w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Saturne
<pb facs="tcp:10409:22"/> On the v day of February in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond houſe of heuen, not ryſen, but to riſe, ſignifieth diſtruction of goo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, Sub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>taunce, Houſes &amp; houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold ſtuffe: and ſignifyeth alſo the ingrate diſobedience of ſeruauntes and labourers: And that the ryche and great men ſhalbe had in no eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation among their ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, and yet many of their ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ſhalbe promoted by them: and alſo the ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers proudly ſhall diſdayn to obey the order and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of their Capitaynes. In lyke maner as Ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gelus teacheth, the Congregation or Counſell of Mars with Iupiter which thei ſhall celebrate or ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely kepe, The .vii. day of April in the morning in the .xi. houſe of heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> betokeneth many euels: as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> darth and death of beaſtes, theft, priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and battayles chiefly vnto the ſubiectes of Aquarius, Alſo Ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nus placed with Mercuri in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſygne of heuen, ſignifieth lacke of ſubſtaunce, the vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly dedes of men ſtynking delytes with women: and that not a few ſecrets ſhalbe diſclo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed,
<pb facs="tcp:10409:22"/> letters ſhall be opened: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whatſoeuer thou doeſt, doo it prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly &amp; wiſely &amp; behold the end.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of plenty and ſcarcytie of grayne, of the lucke of thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges ſpringi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the erth.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THE</hi> eſtate of the Fruyt of the erth ſhalbe indifferent good (god ſo willyng) but Mars much thretneth hurt vnto trees, &amp; ſo ſhal yeld a wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerynge eſtate of all grayne: But for all that, for the habitation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Moone in the fygure coniunctional and for the application of her, a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell after the ſame coniunction to a quadrate aſpecte of Saturne, the price of neceſſary foode ſhall rather diminiſh then encreace: wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the firſt the parte of plentifulnes of the whole yere ſhal fal in the .xii. houſe &amp; in the tryne or thre cornered aſpect of Mercury. But what ſhal not the execrable gredines of gold or money
<pb facs="tcp:10409:23"/> and the curſſed ſwetenes of lucre &amp; vſury defyle &amp; breke? Now I wyll tell you by courſe the ꝑticuler luck of euery thing, as our <hi>VRANIA</hi> hath ben accuſtomed, that is as our heuenly Figure hath ben accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be declared. <hi>VRANIA</hi> is one of the, ix. Muſes. &amp; is by inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation <hi>CELESTIS</hi> Heuenly.</p>
               <p>¶ Great Beſtes and fat ſhall dy Gottes and ſmall Beaſtes ſhall be of lytel valure. ¶ Butter &amp; mylke ſhalbe plentifull and not dere, but it ſhalbe thyn and watery.</p>
               <p>¶ Ryſſe, Wheat, Rye, &amp; other more pleſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Graynes, in growyng men may bewayle the blaſtyng, &amp; in the market vſury. ¶ Secale, Barly, Otes &amp; ſuch lyke, ſhall grow more fortunate, and in price more cheap. ¶ Millium panicum, Myrica, ſhal haue them ſelfes after a waueryng ſorte, as wel in growyng as in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng to the market.</p>
               <p>¶ Cicer, Peaſe. Le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ſhal encreaſe in differently. ¶ Apples, Peares, Peaches, Plummes and Cheryes, for the perel that ſhal fall in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree
<pb facs="tcp:10409:23"/> of their parte, thei ſhalbe ſkant ¶ Haſell nuttes and Wallnuttes lykewyſe ſhalbe ſcarſe and deare. ¶ Beanes, Rapes, Onions and Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>byges ſhal habound greatly.</p>
               <p>¶ Hempe and Flaxe ſhall ſpringe much, but yeld lytell, and therfore ſhalbe deare.</p>
               <p>¶ Honny ſhalbe of indifferent pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, yet very plentyfull, howbeit it ſhalbe watery.</p>
               <p>¶ Wyne ſhalbe indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly priced but the Grapes to come ſhalbe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate in increaſe, becauſe the hore froſtes ſhal hurt them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Metalles.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MARS</hi> in an erthy ſygne beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneth generally corruption of the Mynes, yet neuertheles Golde in ſpring tyme ſhalbe enha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced in price and the vayne of it ſhalbe leſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyred.</p>
               <p>¶ In Somer it ſhalbe of dyuers prices, but it ſhall not enryche the workers thereof.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10409:24"/>
               <p>¶ In Herueſt the price of it ſhal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynne to be leſſe, and the labourers of it ar promyſed perelles. In Wyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter lykewyſe it ſhal fall in price and it ſhalbe dygged out very vnpure. ¶ Syluer in ſpring tyme ſhall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the beſt ſtate, and it ſhallbe as well profitable vnto the worke men as precious vnto the occupiers. In Somer contrary wyſe it ſhall gyue buſynes both to the Merchauntes and Myners.. In Herueſt it ſhall aſcend agayne in byeng. In Wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it ſhalbe indifferently priſed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where. ¶ Quicke Syluer in Spring tyme ſhall be perylouſe in gettyng &amp; of lytell value in eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In Somer it ſhalbe worſe and leſſe plenty than in eſtimation.</p>
               <p>In Herueſt it ſhall be of a good ſtate and dere. In Wynter it ſhall not be equall vnto the ſweate and expences. ¶ Tynne in Spring time ſhalbe equally draune out, that is with out either loſſe or gayne to the byers or ſellers. In Somer it ſhalbe of a good ſtate &amp; much preaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for to be bought.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10409:24"/>
               <p>In herueſt it ſhalbe more habunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, but of lytle pryce. In Winter worſt of all.</p>
               <p>¶ Yron, ſteele, and bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſtone, In ſpryng time ſhalbe of an honeſt rate and not dere. In ſommer lykewiſe: In herueſt as thei ſhalbe made derer ſo ſhall they haue a worſe ſtate, or more vnpure. In winter thei ſhalbe pure, but of litle eſtimation.</p>
               <p>¶ Copper and braſſe in ſpryngti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſhall deminyſhe in pryce, but let the labourers in the Mynes beware perrel, namely the fallyng doune of it. In Somer it ſhall increaſe worſe both in Mynes and merket, And like wyſe in herueſt ſeaſon. In wynter ceaſon it ſhalbe of more value.</p>
               <p>¶ Leade in ſpryngtyme ſhalbe of the pureſt condicion &amp; dere, but not profytable to the workemen. In ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, aſwel the goodnes as the pryce ſhalbe deminiſhed In herueſt yet ſtil it ſhall fall in pryce, and ſhall bryng diſeaſes too the labourers in it.</p>
               <p>In wynter again it ſhalbe better in qualitie, but the pryce thereof ſhall not be inhaunced.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:10409:25"/>
               <head>¶ Of peſtilences and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſickneſſes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THE</hi> aſſendent in the fygure of the reuolution, &amp; Mars lord of the yeare, threaten euil the health of men, ſpeciallye the quadrangale of the bulle, &amp; alſo the croked aſpect of Saturne to the Moone a lytle after the coniunction of the Lightes the Moone goyng before, threaten peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, but yet neither vniuerſall nor great. But ſurely the .vi. houſe ſhall geue many diſeaſes, whote &amp; ſharpe to the which, aſwell the lorde of the yere, as the clyppyng or ioyning to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of the vnfortunate Planetes ſhall puruay ſodayne and vnloked for death of men in ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; luſty age.</p>
               <p>¶ The diſeaſes of Mars ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe or be of moſt ſtrength and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer. In the ſpryng tyme, as are pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, feuers or agues, continuall tertians, <hi>CAVSON</hi> or moſt whot burnyng ague bredde of pure coller in veynes nighe vnto the heart, and differeth from a tertian, that is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb facs="tcp:10409:25"/> engendred in the veynes, but yet far from the hearte, <hi>VARIOLAE</hi> whiche is a diſeaſe that chyldren &amp; young men haue often, but olde men very ſeldome. Eriſipilas whiche is alſo called <hi>IGNISSACER</hi> the holy fier, of ſome S. Antonies fyer, and as Galyn ſaith, it is a ſwelling that commeth of a whote and thyn blood, and is ſumtyme myxed wyth coler, bruſtyng out of blod. The iau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh, whot impoſtemes, madnes, ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines of the preuities, and reines, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the griefes and paynes of the eyes.</p>
               <p>¶ In Somer ſeaſon partly who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſeaſes of the hedde, and peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, hedde aches, partly paynes of the ſhinnes with Saturnyn, or diſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Saturne, as the leproſy, <hi>EC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TICA</hi> or conſumption, <hi>MELAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHOLIA</hi> or madnes. <hi>THE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NESMVS</hi> which is a continuall deſyre too exonerate or too eaſe the wombe that maye neither be defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red nor eſcaped: and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any thyng is voided it ſhalbe very litle and that moſt commenlye blood, the fyſtule, the cancre, &amp; <hi>STRVMAE,</hi> which
<pb facs="tcp:10409:26"/> are heard impoſtumes, ſumtimes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng in the necke, and ſumtyme vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the armehooles, and ſumtyme aboute the preuie partes, and differ from Glandule in matter onlye, for <hi>GLANDVLE</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of flegme and <hi>STRVMAE</hi> of Melancolye.</p>
               <p>¶ Harueſt ſeaſon ſhalbe ſtayned very much with the peines or grefes of the feete and thighes, palſy, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynges, ytche, and with imflamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the eyes.</p>
               <p>¶ The Wynter ſhalbe noyfull, with rotten feuers, falling ſickenes defnes, and with diſeaſes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, of <hi>DIAPHRAGMA</hi> which is a lytle ſynnowe ſkynne ioynyng to the maw, and with infirmities of the belly and wyth flegme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of peace and warre</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THE</hi> warrier &amp; wrothful Mars Lord of this yere ſhal ſend furth in violence of anger &amp; ragyng wod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes euery wher vnto the <hi>CAPRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NISTES</hi> or ſubiectes to the ſigne of the Goate, and to the whole qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drangle
<pb facs="tcp:10409:26"/> of it, all vexacions and tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, ſo that lytle reſt ſhall be lefte theym, but they ſhall ſteadefaſtlye loke for all artillery and weapens, warre, robbery, diminiſhing of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, manſlaughter, &amp; killyng: which miſchiefe aboue all thyng the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame Mars with Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne ſhall ſharpen and moue vnto mankynde wyth fyerſe ſworde, as Hiſpale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wryteth. And as the gret ſlaughter fallyng in the .xii. houſe of heauen, whyche is of impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and emnities, ſhall rayſe vp euery wher vehement and cruel aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaultes, and fraudulent and ſubtyl batelles: ſo ſhall, the greate Ecli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of the Sunne in the ſigne of the waterer that was in the yeare. M. <hi>CCCCC.</hi> xliiii. ſtir vp no ſmal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbation or hurly burlye at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this our yere, and ſo ſhal take his leaue of them for euer. The great hurtes &amp; ſedicions of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men people, are too be feared in the Southpart of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde. After Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauien, when Mars ſhalbe myxed with the Sunne, in a ſharpe aſpecte
<pb facs="tcp:10409:27"/> whiche ſhall fall aboute the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of Maye and September.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of the perticuler fortunes of men aſwel in proſperitie as inaduerſitie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ALTHOVGH</hi> it be impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to the Aſtronomer to ſhew before the particuler natures of all vnſeperable thinges, and to diſcuſſe the ſecret and hidden operations &amp; influences of al the ſterres euen too the vttermoſt poynte, (which thyng Ptolomy knewe,) yet is it manyfeſt that diuers of thoſe thynges which yerly we doo marke and intitle, and that we eyther promyſe or threaten in oure ſymple Aſtrologicall Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtications, not at all aduentures but by the ordre and courſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens mercked and ſtudied vpon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, do chaunce after. And therfore accordyng to the accuſtomed maner we wyl ſet furth clerely and playn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto you as nye as we can, aſwel the fortune of ſuch people as are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:10409:27"/> the zodiac or .xii. ſignes, as alſo to declare bi ordre the diſpoſicion of the planetes. Therfore whatſoeuer mortal man either nowe borne or to be borne ſhal perceiue how to count the conuerſions or reuolutions of their yeres &amp; birthe figures of their aſcendentes in anye one daye of the daies vnder ſpecified &amp; noted. They if thei cannot wiſely auoyde nor pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſuffre and bear the euyl for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous lyfe or diſpleſures of body iminent and at hand, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cal vnto <hi>GOD</hi> that he of his great mercy, wil either take them ſhortly awaye, or elles of hys fauourable goodnes to mittigate &amp; aſwage the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The infortunate and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luckie dayes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> birthes and reuolutions of Men, for the yeare of our lord. M.D.xlvi.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THE</hi> .iii. daye of Ianuary. the .v and .xiiii. of Februari. The .iiii. xx. and .xxx. of March, The .vii. and xxx, of April. the .iii. x. xvii &amp; .xxx. of
<pb facs="tcp:10409:28"/> Maye. The .ii. &amp; .xvii. of Iune. The ix. xxii. and .xxv. of Auguſte. The .i. ii. x. and .xviii. of September. The xxv. and .x vii. of October. The .viii xiii. and .xxiiii. of December.</p>
               <p>¶ And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie wiſe, better chaunce ſhal happen to them that ether now are begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or ſhall haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of their reuolution vnto their age paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in anye of the dayes folowyng: for theſe luckye dayes not only lede a ryght bleſſed lyfe, but alſo ſhalbe preſerued, heped vp and fylled with ryches and dignitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The fortunate and luckye dayes in birthes and reuolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions of Men for this yeare be theſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THE</hi> xxix. day of Ianuary. The ix. xi. and .xxviii. of March, The xxii. of April. The .xviii. of Maye, The .xxiii. of Iune. The .xvii. and xxxiii. of Auguſt. The .x. of Septem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber. The, v. of October, The .xv. and xxviii. of Nouember, and the .ii. day of December.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:10409:28"/>
               <head>¶ Of the ſubiectes of the vii. planetes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THE</hi> black ſwart perſons ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte to Saturne as the Iewes, the Mores, ſolitarye perſons, aged perſones, Huſbande men, Maſons, Shomakers, Porters, and Brycke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, Glouers, Corriers, Bery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of dead coarſes, Dunge fermers and clenſers of Maſers, and al wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kers of ſuche groſſe workes.</p>
               <p>¶ In ſpring tyme ſhalbe troubled with diſeaſes in their fere Alſo thei ſhal fynde greate vnfaythfulnes in their ſeruauntes. And further, the ſayd Saturniſtes ſhalbe gredy and deſirefull of the ryches that ryche perſons haue. In ſummer thei ſhal ſuffre loſſe and hinderaunce. In her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueſt ceaſon, thei ſhalbe obſcure in their religion, and wrapped in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny couenauntes and bandes, but let them beware of cold diſeaſes of the vttter partes of their body.</p>
               <p>¶ In wynter thei ſhalbe in theyr beſt ſtate and condicion, for thei ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:10409:29"/> beholde, wyth an vnwyllyng eye, the death deſerued of the vnfaithful and the power of the ſubiectes of the Sun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>¶ The roaſe coulered perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to Iupiter, as Patriarches, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalles, Biſhoppes, Iudges, Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialles, Councellers, and all other learned and wyſe men, for their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued wyſedomes, ſhalbe had in much eſtimation and honour.</p>
               <p>¶ The hye coulered perſons and other ſubiect to Mars, as Turkes, Tartarians, Souldiers of al ſortes and nations, Capitaines of warre, Sargeauntes, Phiſicians, Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyans, Alchamiſtes, Yrone ſmythes Turme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tours, Hangeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Butchers, Thefes, and whoſoeuer chiefly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyght in fyre and Yrone. In ſpryng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme yf thei bee not diſeaſed in the ſhoulders and legges, thei ſhall go in meſſage or iourney, they ſhal war and ſhal purchaſe and get great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyt of the <hi>VENERIANS.</hi> In ſummer thei ſhal vſe ſecret matters and many of theym ſhalbe occupied in Mariages and Marchaundyſe,
<pb facs="tcp:10409:29"/> In herueſt let them bewar leſt their pride and glorye begyn to fayle. In winter thei ſhal get both the fauour of the <hi>IOVISTES</hi> and <hi>VENE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIANS,</hi> and their fortune ſhalbe increaſed, and they ſhalbe pregnant and of quicke wyttes to al thyng be gunne or taken in hand: but let them beware of diſeaſes in the head.</p>
               <p>¶ The beautiful perſons and good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly viſages, and al other of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties ſubiect to the Sunne, as Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, Kynges, Prynces, Lordes Knightes and Gentilme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In ſpring tyme, through the enuye of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnians or ſubiectes to Saturne, whiche are the Turckes, thei ſhalbe diſquieted. The ſummer ſhalbe ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to theim, yet ſhal thei reigne in large benefites and great renoume. In herueſt thei ſhalbe pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and ioyous: but the winter ſhalbe ſuſpet to them.</p>
               <p>¶ The deintie chyldren of Venus with other ſubiect vnto her as Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſyns, Gentiles, al Muſicians, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng men, Minſtrels, Plaiers, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of precious ſtone, Brotherers,
<pb facs="tcp:10409:30"/> Steiners, and Diers, Taylers, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, young Damoſels, ſingle Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and al Womenkind. In ſpring tyme thei ſhal wander from place to place, and ſhalbe as it were wanton but yet they ſhal profit by the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians. In ſommer they ſhalbe hyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered of the Solaria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and alſo thei ſhal lament the iniuries and wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Saturnians: thei ſhalbe made glad, and delighted by their frendes. In herueſt they ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyt and waxe ryche, and not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſom fauor of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iouiſts, thei ſhal geue dylige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to haue chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In winter thei ſhal proſper through the fauour of fryndes, and ſuch thinges as thei loke not for, thei ſhal obteyn preue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the ayde of the Mercians: let remyng wemen kepe theym ſelues warely in ſpryng tyme and harueſt. ¶ Such as are ſubiect to Mercury as Marchauntes, Scrybes, Poetes Aſtronymers, Geometricians, Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, Southſaiers, ſtudientes of Artes <hi>Printers,</hi> Paynters, and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticaries. In ſpryngtime thei ſhalbe heauy, ydle, and rechles, of euil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicion
<pb facs="tcp:10409:30"/> &amp; altogether goyng back. In ſomer thei ſhalbe geuen clerly vnto godly wiſedome and holy matters, without pompe. In herveſt thei ſhal multiply in ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaryes. In winter thei being gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with ſorowe of the Lunarians ſubiectes to the Moone, and ſhut or cloſed vp, may not diſpute in theyr artes: but howſoeuer it ſhalbe they ſhalbe holpen by the Saturnians</p>
               <p>¶ The whyte ſunnes of the Mone and all her other ſubiectes, as infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior perſons &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men people, houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyfes, or Matrons, Weme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne, Chaferers, Millers, Bathke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, Mariners, Fyſhers, Idell go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers aboute, Carriers, meſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, and al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> delighteth in water, In ſpryng tyme they ſhal proſper, but thei ſhal be afrayed of wyles and guyles of the Saturnia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and the open miſchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes and euil doing of the Mercians In ſomer thei ſhalbe ſycke of bodye and not ſtrong in other matters, to which aſwel the Saturnians as So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtes ſhal do their cure. Herueſt ſhal be indifferent to them, but they ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:10409:31"/> receiue hurt by Mariages. In win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thei ſhal fal into hinderaunce of ſubſtaunce, and hatred of the Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, in their promotions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The ſonnes of the .xii. ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the zodiac.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THOSE</hi> that be borne vnder A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. In ſpryngtime ſhal optain frendſhyp of the Iouiſtes and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnians, but of the Mercians hate and thei ſhalbe diſpoſed to paſtime, and pleaſures, but thei ſhalbe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with diſeaſes. In ſomer death and loſſes ſhall noye theim. In her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt thei ſhal finde fryndes and hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, but the Mercurians ſhalbe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries and enemies to theim.</p>
               <p>In wynter thei ſhall ſuffre hurt by woundes, and other diſeaſes: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many frendſhyppes, thei ſhal perceiue many lies. The infortunat and euil dayes vnto them ſhalbe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .xvii. of Februarye to the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of April, from the .xi. of Iuly, to the .ii. of September, and agayne,
<pb facs="tcp:10409:31"/> from the .xvii. of Nouember vntyl the ende of the yeare.</p>
               <p>¶ Thei that be borne vnder Tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus. In ſpring tyme ſhalbe diſpoſed to Mariages and other buſines and they ſhal optayne the fauour of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but not wythout conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cions. In ſomer thei ſhall receiue promotions both for theyr wiſedome and honeſt behauoure. In herueſt thei ſhal get fryndſhip of the Luniſtes, benefites of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iouians, and good reporte: but howſoeuer it be the Venerians ſhal be moued agaynſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wynter, ſhal be diſpleaſaunt and daungerous to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. They ſhal loke for euyl fortune the fyrſt .iii. dayes of Ianuary, and from the .i. daye of Apryl vntyll the xiiii. of Maye.</p>
               <p>¶ Thei that are borne vnder Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini. In ſpryngtyme ſhalbe vexed or greuyd with the malice of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnians, and ſhal receiue hurte. In ſomer they ſhalbe vexed in theyr of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and promotions on all ſydes. In Herueſt heauines, ſlaunders, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies and priſonmentes ſhal vexe them euery where. In wynter they
<pb facs="tcp:10409:32"/> ſhal proſpere in their iourneies, and ſhal ſtudy and delight in godlye ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes. The whole yeare ſhalbe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate and ful of perell vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the ſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re of Saturne, but let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take hede to them ſelfes &amp; to theirs from the .iiii. of Ianuary tyl y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xvii of Februarye. Alſo, from the .xv. of May, tyl the .x. of Iuly. Fynallye, from the .iiii. of September tyll the xvi. of Nouember.</p>
               <p>¶ Thei that are borne vnder Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer Springtime and winter thei ſhal tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uail. Thei ſhalbe very ſtudious and deſireous of good learning, but thei ſhal haue the Mercians enemyes to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In ſomer thei ſhal haue louyng felowes and frendes, chefly the Ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nerians, and thei ſhal proſpere. In herueſt likewiſe thei ſhalbe in good condition, yet let them obſerue the tyme as it is ſayd in Aries.</p>
               <p>¶ Thei that are borne vnder Leo In ſpryngtyme ſhal make an end of great iourneis, &amp; ſhal procure thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to Goddes honor, and manye of them ſhall increaſe in riches. In ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer agayne, thei ſhalbe afrayed of
<pb facs="tcp:10409:32"/> enemies, leſt thei ſhould be put from their dignities. In Herueſt they be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng gredy of ryches ſhall enter into bandes, and ſhalbe buſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in maters of their frendes. In Wynter they ſhall proſpere very well, except the Iouiſtes, Venerians &amp; Mercuria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s entermedle w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them. But lette them be wyſe &amp; circumſpect in the tymes that are mentioned in the Bull.</p>
               <p>¶ They that ar borne vnder Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go the Virgyn, In ſpring tyme ſhal floriſh, if the Saturnians hynder them not. Somer ſhalbe noyſome &amp; inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modious to them. In Herueſt alſo they ſhall ſuffer diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities in the inheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of their predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours: But Wi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter ſhalbe ſomwhat more fauorable to theym: howbeit they ſhall haue lyke Iuditial days all this yere, as hath the ſubiectes of Gemini.</p>
               <p>They that be borne vnder Libra the Balaunce, in ſpring tyme ſhalbe ſomtyme mery &amp; ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>time heauy, both among their enmies &amp; fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des in dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently. In Sommer they ſhalbe full of newes, and at diuerſe conten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cions
<pb facs="tcp:10409:33"/> with their brethern. In Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt thei ſhalbe diſpoſed to wiſdom and geuen to delycatnes and apt to generation by the helpe of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnians. In Wynter, they beyng compaſſed with enemies in marcial affayres, ſhall behaue them ſelues politickly. Yet notwithſtanding let them fere the days y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ar ſet in Aries.</p>
               <p>¶ They that be borne vnder Scorpio, the Scorpion. In Spring tyme ſhal proſpere. In Somer they ſhalbe ſeruiſable vnto their Paren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes &amp; nygh kynſfolke, and obedient to the Law of their Countrey.</p>
               <p>In Herueſt they ſhalbe mery &amp; ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the pleſures of the fleſh and other paſtymes, by the fauor of the Venerians. In Wynter they being enriched with the goodes of the Lu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſtes &amp; Mercurians ſhall not paſſe vpon lernyng. Let them walke cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpectly in thoſe times which ar had in ſuſpicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Taurus the Bul.</p>
               <p>¶ They that are borne vnder Sagittarius, the Shoter, ſhal this yere ſuffer diſpleaſures of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnians: but the Dragons tayle
<pb facs="tcp:10409:33"/> in this Signe ſignifieth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon of ſome great Perſonages, In Spring time thei ſhal profite lytel. In Somer they ſhall ſuffer loſſe of their inheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: but they ſhal get the good wylles of the come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peple. In Herueſt thei being greued with ſyckneſſes &amp; found treſpaſſers &amp; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders ſhal hardly eſcape the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty of Mars. In Wynter thei ſhal gladly obey vnto Lawes: But let them be circumſpecte in iorneyeng, and aboue al that they take hede of the ſuſpect dayes mencioned before in Gemini.</p>
               <p>¶ They that be borne vnder Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricorne the Goat, In Spring tyme whyle they contend &amp; fall out with their neybours and brethern, ſhall ſuffer loſſe of their goodes by the Marcians. In Somer, their chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren &amp; heyres &amp; al their other ioyes ſhalbe contrary to them: &amp; ſo ſhall it be alſo both to the Mercurians &amp; Marcians. In Herueſt, they geui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them ſelfes to mariages &amp; merchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diſes ſhal purchaſe the diſpleaſure of the Mercuria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. In Wynter thei
<pb facs="tcp:10409:34"/> hating the Marcia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhal not let to talke frely i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maters of lerni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. Thei ſhal haue very euyl fortune in thoſe euyl &amp; ſuſpect dayes that ar expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Aries, ¶ They that be borne vnder Aquarius the Waterer: In Springtyme they ſhal lede their ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues amongeſt their neybours indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly. In ſomer they ſhalbe helth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full. In Herueſt they ſhall go from place to place for the deth of the Ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nerians &amp; Luniſtes. Wynter ſhalbe good to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fathers &amp; i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>heritours of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cuntrey, yet the power of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> luniſts ſhal repugne them. Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beware the iudicial dais reherſed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bul. ¶ They that be born vnder Piſces the Fyſſhes. In Spring tyme they ſhal proue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fortune of the cuntrey But the Saturniſtes ſhall maligne them. In Somer thei ſhal fere war. In herueſt they ſhal proſper except the Marcians &amp; Saturniſtes hyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them. Wynter ſhalbe indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to them. But let them take hede to the contrary dayes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioned before in Gemi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ni, the Twynnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:10409:34"/>
               <head>¶ Vnder what quadrangle of the Zodiach ſignes euery Region and Citie is ſituate</head>
               <div n="1" type="quadrangle">
                  <head>The firſt Quadrangle</head>
                  <p>¶ ARIES the Ram hath as Ptolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me writeth theſe Regions and Cities, Cocloſyre, Paleſtin, Britayne, hye Frau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nce, Braccate, Garmany, Baſterny. And after the myndes of late wryters, The lande of Pole the leſſer, The duchye of Burgundy, Sileſy the hyer, Sweu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>land. And of Cities, Neaples, Florence, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pua, Ferrarie, Vincenty, Verone, Parga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye, Imola, Pauye, Brunſwicke, Traiect Lyndoa, Parcyuncle, Vineſtrace. Craco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy, Marſelies, Ceaſer auguſtꝰ, ¶ Cancer the crab hath as Ptolome ſayth, Numi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di. Afryk, Bythimi, Phrigia, Colche, Car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thage. After the later wryters, the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dme of Fraunce, the kyngdome of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, the kyngdome of Granate, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Burgundy, Pruſſy, Hollande, Seland. And of Cites. Conſtantynople, Thunes, Venice, Myllayn, Geneue, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, Piſas, Lubeck, Treuerne, Maide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge, Gorlityne, Berne, Yorke, Saynt Andrewes, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Libra the balaunce hath by Ptolomies ſai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng, Bactrian, Caſpy, Serim, Thebaide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oaſin, and Troglodit. After the later wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Acthiope, Turky, Auſtrige: Elſary
<pb facs="tcp:10409:35"/> Sundgauye, Leuonye, Sebandye, and Delphynate. And of Cytyes, Cayl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, Lande, Sueſſe, Placentyne, Argentine Vienne of Auſtrige, Franckford, Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſch, Spires, Hal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, of Suene, Hailprun, W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in, Landſhute, Fryſynge, Moſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chye, F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ldkyrchy, of Rhery, Arelate, and Luſhborne.</p>
                  <p>Capricornus the Got hath, by Ptolomy Indy. Arian, Gedroſye, Macydon, Illyre Tracy. After the later wryters, Boſſne, Albani, Bulgari, Grece, Lithuani, Maſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, Saroni, Churius, Heſſi, Marcas, and Bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>burgh a ꝓte of Stiri. And of Cites Anconi, Fauant, Torton, Foroli, Auguſt, Vindelice, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtance, Iuliac, Cleuoni, Bei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge, Gaunte, Machlin. Vilue, Oxforde, &amp; the Iſles Orchadas,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="quadrangle">
                  <head>The ſecond Quadrangle.</head>
                  <p>Taurus the Bul hath as Ptolomy ſaith Parthy, Mede, Perſyde, the Iſles Cicla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, Cipreſe, the ſea coſtes of the leſſer Aſia. After later writters, Pole the greter white Ruſſy, Campany, Rhete, Helvece, Francon, Lutheringe, Hyreland, &amp; a parte of the Suetes. And of Cities, Bononi Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nas, Mantua, Tar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>myte, Parme, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norme, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hurege, Lucerne, Herbipolym, Metime, Bryxin the chief citie of Hiſtri.</p>
                  <p>Leo the Lyon hath by Ptolemy, Phe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyce, Calde, Orchin, Italy, Galli, Togate, Sycile, Apule. After the later writers Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heme
<pb facs="tcp:10409:35"/> kyngdom, parte of Turcky, Aemyle, Sabine. And of Cities, Damaſco, Rome, Rauenne, Syracuſe, Peruſy, Cremone, Prage, Vlme, Confluence, Lince, Kremſe.</p>
                  <p>Scorpius the Scorpion hath by Ptolo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>my, Matagonite, Commagei. Cappa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doce, Syrie, Iury, Idumea, Mauritane, &amp; Getule. By the later writers, Nortuege, Suetye in the weſt, Cathalone, Baueyre the hyer, &amp; Foroiule. And of Cities Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pezonte, Algere, Aquile, Padwey, Vrbane Piſtore, Camerne, Brixye, Taruſre, Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſane, Gedan, Lypſye, Monace, Aichſtade, Vienne, Allobroge, Valence in Hyſpane.</p>
                  <p>Aquarius the Waterer hath after Pto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lomy, Oxiane, Sogdirne, Araby the ſtony Azanſe, Aethyope, &amp; Sarmace. After the later writers, greate Tartery, Danye, red Ruſſy, Amaroby, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſouth parte of Suece, Walache, Pedeſmount, Weſtphale, Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelaunce peple. And of Cities, Alkayr or Memphym, Ironemounte, Piſaure, Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente, Hamburgh, Breme, Saltzeburge, Ingoldſtand &amp; a lytell parte of Bauere.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="quadrangle">
                  <head>The thyrd Quadrangle.</head>
                  <p>Gemini the Twynne hath by Ptolomy Hyrcany Armenye Margiane Cyrenaice prouince Merinarice, Aegipte the lower. After the later writers the kyngdom of England, Sardine, Brabant, Wirtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berge duchy, Flandres, &amp; Lumberdy, And of Cities, Viterby, Ceſene, Taurine, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye,
<pb facs="tcp:10409:36"/> Vercel, Norinbergh, Louen, Magu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce Bamberge, Bruges in Flaundres, Villace Kitzinge, Haſſforde, London, &amp; Corduba.</p>
                  <p>Virgo the Virgine hath by Ptolomy Meſopotamy, Babilon, Aſſyria, Grece A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaie and Crete. And after the later wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trs Cicile, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reace, Athens duchy, Caren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teane, Sylete the lower, Atheſane proui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce a parte of Rhene, Rhodes. And of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, gret Alexander, Hieruſalem, Corinth Papy, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>red, Cumas, Brunduſe, Vratiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laue, Erdford, Baſil, Haidelberge, Dagni Parys, Lyons, &amp; Tholos.</p>
                  <p>Sagittarius the ſhoter hath by Ptho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lome, Araby the lucky, Thirhene, Celtica Spaine. Bi y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> later writers Portugall Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>garye. Denmarke, Norwaye, Sclauone, Myſna. And of Cities Volaterre, Muti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Colyn, Aggrippe, Stutgard, Rotenburge Tubare, Indeburge, Bude, Gaſchone, Narbon, Auinion, and Tolete.</p>
                  <p>Piſces the Fiſhes haue after Ptolomy Phazam, Nazamonite, Garama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tice, Lyde Cilice, &amp; Pamphile. And by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> later writers Calabr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Norway. And of Cities, Pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ynſbourgh, Wormes, Rawane, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtella, and Hyſpalim.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="colophon">
            <p>LONDINI Ex officina Richardi Graftoni clariſſimo Principi Edouardo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Typographia</p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="lat">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cum priuilegio ad impri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mendum ſolum</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb facs="tcp:10409:36"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
